<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon a pretended answer to Mijn Heer Fagel's letter</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07985330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07985330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40747</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40747)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1214:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon a pretended answer to Mijn Heer Fagel's letter</title>
                  <author>N. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>p. 343-362.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to N.T.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stewart, James, --  Sir, 1635-1713. --  Answer to a letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40747:1"/>
            <pb n="344" facs="tcp:40747:2"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>reſted in the Affairs of that Republick; ſo by nothing hath he more merited an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal eſteem and praiſe from all Proteſtants, and acquitted himſelf more worthily towards God and their Serene <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> than by that <hi>Letter</hi> wherein he was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured to declare their thoughts, and in which he hath with ſo much wiſdom, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and convincing light, expreſſed both their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Sentiments, and his own, as well concerning the Engliſh Laws, the Papiſts may, and the Diſſenters ought to be favoured with the Repeal of, as concerning thoſe, which no wiſe Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt deſires to have reſcinded, and which to humour the Papiſts with the Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of, were no leſs than to expoſe the Nation to ruine, and to lay the Reformed Religion open to be totally ſubverted.</p>
            <p>Now this Excellent <hi>Letter,</hi> and which hath produced all the good Effects that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men long'd for, but knew not before how to compaſs, our <hi>Anonymous</hi> Anſwerer is pleaſed with an Indignation and angry Reſentment, and in hopes to exaſperate his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> againſt their Serene Highneſſes, to ſtile <hi>a kind of Manifeſt in reference to moſt important Affairs, which even Mr. Stewart,</hi> who in obedience to the injunctions of his Soveraign, had with ſo much importunity ſollicited their Highneſſes Opinion about the Repeal of the Penal and Teſt Laws, he ſays, <hi>could not have expected.</hi> And of whom to teſtifie his exact and intimate knowledge, and to recompence him for the unfortunate ſervice he had been employed in, and to encourage his readineſs to future drudgery, he is pleaſed by a creation of his own, as being the Subſtitute of the Fountain of Honour, to confer the Title of <hi>Dr.</hi> upon. But certainly had this <hi>Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Writer the ſenſe and prudence of an ordinary man, he would not under the preſent conjuncture of Affairs, talk of <hi>Manifeſts,</hi> nor put people in mind of them at a ſeaſon, when moſt perſons of all ranks and qualities are ſo much diſguſted, and when they at <hi>Whitehall</hi> are ſo laviſh in their provocations towards <hi>ſome,</hi> who if they were not ſtrangely fortified againſt all tincture of Reſentment, are known to be capable of doing them irreparable prejudice, and who by ſuch a <hi>Manifeſt</hi> as there is cauſe enough to emit, might not only diſturb their proceedings, but with the greateſt facility blow up at once both all their hopes and projections. I would fain know of this modeſt and diſcreet Gentleman, whether if their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> had ordered a Letter to be written, declarative of their Opinion for the Abrogation of the <hi>Teſts,</hi> by what name he would have judged it worthy to be called, and whether if he had beſtowed upon it the Title of a <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> he would have thereby intended to faſten upon it an imputation of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and reproach? All good men have reaſon mightily to bewail their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> condition, ſeeing according to this rate of proceeding towards them, it is in the power of the Papal Eccleſiaſticks in <hi>England,</hi> when they pleaſe, to prevail upon the <hi>King</hi> to reduce them to the uneaſie circumſtances, either of offending againſt their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or of diſpleaſing him. For there is no more requiſite towards the bringing them into this unhappy <hi>Dilemma,</hi> but that <hi>Father Peters,</hi> or any other of the Tribe who have an Aſcendency over his Majeſty, do perſuade him to deſire their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Thoughts, in reference to ſuch particulars, wherein it is neither conſiſtent with their Religious Principles, nor agreeable with their Honour, to comply with his Majeſties Judgment and Inclinations. For if in prudence they decline the returning of an Anſwer, they are ſure not only to be cenſured, as guilty of neglect, incivility and rudeneſs, but they do thereby adminiſter an advantage to their Enemies, of diffuſing reports to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice thro' the Nation, as if they approved all thoſe Court-methods, which for no other reaſon, ſave upon the meer motives of reſpect and wiſdom, they avoided openly to diſallow. And if on the other hand, they ſuffer themſelves to be overcome by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and thereupon give an Anſwer agreeable to the Dictates of their own minds, but which is found to interfere with the prepoſſeſſions wherewith his Majeſty is imbued, then their Lot is, to have it called by the unkind and ignominious Title of a <hi>Manifeſt.</hi> One would think that <hi>Letter</hi> ought to have been mentioned by a ſoſter name, if we do but conſider its being written not only with the utmoſt modeſty that becomes the Relation Their Highneſſes ſtand in to the King, and which is any ways agreeable to their own quality, but that it is enforced with all the Reaſons, that may ſerve to demonſtrate that their Opinion is the reſult of conviction and judgment, and not the effect of humour, nor a ſentiment they are meerly determined unto by their intereſt. But we ſee no Term is too hard to be beſtowed upon a Paper that hath ſo much prejudiced the Prieſts in their deſigns, and laid ſo great an obſtruction in the way of thoſe methods, which they had propoſed to themſelves, for the robbing <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>And whereas our Author tells us, that tho' <hi>Mr. Stewart did not account himſelf obliged to anſwer Monſieur</hi> Fagel's <hi>Letter yet one who extreamly eſteems and honoureth Mr.</hi> Stewart, <hi>thinks the Publick too much concerned, not to have the weakneſs of the reaſonings in it detected,
<pb n="345" facs="tcp:40747:2"/>and to have it made appear that the inferences deduced from them are no ways convincing.</hi> I can eaſily believe that Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi> did not judge himſelf obliged to anſwer the <hi>Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary's Letter,</hi> and all men do account it a piece of wiſdom in him to forbear endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring it. For tho' he be much better qualified for ſuch an undertaking than our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, yet he could not but be ſenſible that it was not to be attempted with any hope of ſucceſs. And if our Author had been endow'd with any meaſure of diſcretion, he would have applied himſelf to any other Employment, rather than have betaken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to writing, being a thing which Nature never intended him for, and eſpecially upon a Subject ſo far above the reach of his underſtanding, and againſt a diſcourſe of that ſolid and well-digeſted ſtrength, that even the Reverend Fathers, whoſe <hi>Letter-carrier</hi> he uſed to be (if we be not ſtrangely miſtaken in the Gentleman had ſo much wit as not to attack it. As knowing that notwithſtanding all their Art in Sophiſtry, they muſt have come off baffled; and that their falſe colours would have been eaſily detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the beams of that light, which dart themſelves forth in all the parts of that excellent Paper. And I dare farther ſay, that as Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi> will never much value himſelf, upon the being eſteemed by one either of this Gentleman's Religious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, or of his intellectual Accompliſhments; ſo I can never think that he can be ſo much degenerated from what he formerly was, as to obtain the approbation of his mind, to return any conſiderable degree of honour to a perſon who upon all accounts does ſo little merit it, unleſs it be that he may poſſibly challenge it by vertue of an undeſerved Title, and of a Character that he is exceeding ill qualified for.</p>
            <p>However, ſeeing Fools will be medling, tho' they are ſure to come by the worſt, I ſhall reduce all I have to ſay in Caſtigation of this vain and preſumptuous man, to the <hi>ſeven</hi> following heads. (1.) His Falſifications in reference to ſeveral parts of <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel's Letter.</hi> (2.) His Injuſtice to Their Highneſſes the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the hidden ſpleen he every where ventureth to expreſs againſt them. (3.) His ſlanderous Calumnies againſt the States of theſe Provinces, and how he ſtudies to excite their Roman Catholick Subjects to diſturb the Peace and Tranquillity of this Country. (4) His Shameleſs Impudence in endeavouring to impoſe upon the World, as if the Proteſtant Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> were concluded by Their Highneſſes to ſtand hereafter involved in the ſame rank and condition with the Papiſts. (4.) His Publiſhing the Villany of the Romiſh Church, and proclaiming the Injuſtice and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of the moſt Eminent Papal Monarchs, while he pretends to commend and juſtifie the proceeding of his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain.</hi> (6.) His egregious Ignorance in relation to Government, Laws, Cuſtoms, and matters of Fact. <hi>(Laſtly)</hi> The ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ingratitude of the Papiſts towards Their Royal Highneſſes for all that Grace, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Eaſe, which they were willing to have allowed unto them.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>firſt,</hi> 'Tis known to be a received Principle among the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> of the <hi>Society,</hi> that it is at moſt but a venial ſin, to detract from, miſrepreſent, and calumniate thoſe whom they either take to be their Enemies, or do conceive to have done them any ways a prejudice. And tho' the Opinion authoriſing ſuch a practice, be condemned by a <hi>Bull</hi> of the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> bearing date <hi>Anno</hi> 1679. yet our Author is more a Vaſſal to the <hi>Ignatian Order,</hi> than upon the Authority of one whom the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> do ſo little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, to forbear putting a Doctrine into exerciſe, which he hath been ſo well inſtructed in by theſe Reverend Fathers, and eſpecially when he finds it ſo conduceable to his deſign and intereſt. What can be remoter from Truth as well as Ingenuity, than to charge <hi>Monſieur Fagel with confining the name of Proteſtants in</hi> England, <hi>only to thoſe of the Conformable Communion, and with excluding the Diſſenters from the glorious priviledge of that appellation?</hi> For tho' it be true, that thro' the hatred and violence of the late King and his preſent Majeſty to the Fanaticks, and by vertue of their Commands to a Company of Mercenary, timorous and ſervile Juſticiaries and Officers it hath ſome time come to paſs that the Laws which were originally enacted, and only intended againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> have been executed upon <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> yet all men know that to have been a perverſion of Juſtice, ſeeing in all the Statutes to the Penalties whereof they were made obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they are ſtill conſidered and acknowledged for <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and made liable to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings by no other Title than that of perſons differing from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in matter of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and about <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Rites</hi> of External Worſhip. Nor is there one word in <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi>'s Letter, whereby they are precluded from that ſtile, or any ways repreſented as unworthy of it. While they ſtand obnoxious to ſeveral Laws, in which the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have no concernment, nor are in any danger from; it was impoſſible to avoid the giving them a name by which they might be diſtinguiſhed from thoſe of the Legal and National Communion. And ſo tender hath the <hi>Penſionary</hi> been of charactering them by any offenſive or harſh denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that he hath not ſo much as once in his whole Letter called them <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> tho'
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:40747:3"/>it be an appellation that hath been vulgarly affixed to them; but he hath choſen always to denominate them by the name of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> which is not only the ſofteſt Term they can be deſcribed by, but that which themſelves have elected as the ſtile by which they are willing to be diſcriminated from their fellow Proteſtants, with whom they differ in ſome few and little particulars. And many of them being people, whoſe Principles are coincident and agreeable with theirs of the Legal Eſtabliſhment in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in whoſe Fellowſhip <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi> is known to be; it could not have entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the thoughts of any ſave one of our Authors Intellectuals and Integrity, either to charge upon him or ſo much as to imagine, that he ſhould be ſo injurious to himſelf and to the Dutch Churches, as to preclude thoſe from the liſt of Proteſtants. But whether this calumnious charge and falſification, be the fruit of an Iriſh Underſtanding, or of Papal Sincerity, or the effect of both, I ſhall leave others to judge, who may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly know this Author, better than I pretend to do. Only this I ſhall add, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds with the ſame wit and honeſty as he hath begun. For from Their Highneſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that they cannot agree to the Repeal of the <hi>Teſts,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi>'s there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſaying, that theſe Laws inflict not any mulct or penalty upon the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but that they are only means of ſecuring the Reformed Religion, thro' contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proviſions by which men are to be accounted qualified for Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to bear publick Offices; our Author does by a ſtrange kind of falſification and calumny, faſten upon him his having affirmed, <hi>That the Non-conformiſts are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted dangerous Enemies of the State, and not to be admitted into any Publick Employments.</hi> He muſt either be of a very unuſual and perverſe frame of mind, or extreamly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the nature of thoſe Laws, and the Terms wherein they are enacted, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways it is impoſſible he ſhould imagine how the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are capable of receiving pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice by them. Seeing all required by thoſe Laws toward the qualifying perſons to ſit in Parliament, and to exerciſe Offices in Church and State, is only to declare that they <hi>do believe there is not any Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine, at or after the Conſecration by any perſons whatſoever; and that the Invocation of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>or any other Saint; and the Sacrifice of the Maſs, as they are now uſed in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>are Superſtitious and Idolatrous.</hi> And this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration the Non-conformiſts are of all people, the moſt inclinable and forward to make, and therefore very far by vertue of thoſe Statutes from ſtanding incapable of any Truſt, Office, and Employment, that other Subjects are admitted unto. Nor hath there been a Proteſtant Diſſenter ſince the firſt hour that theſe Laws were enacted, that ever ſcrupled to take the <hi>Teſts,</hi> or that was precluded from Office and Employment for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing them. But on the contrary, ſeveral of the moſt famous Diſſenters, ſuch as Sir <hi>John Hartop,</hi> Alderman <hi>Love,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Eyles,</hi> perſons who at all times have kept at the greateſt diſtance from Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of her Forms and Ceremonies, are known to have chearfully made the Declaration contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws, and thereupon to have ſit as Members in divers Parliaments. And as a further demonſtration of the impudence and diſhoneſty of our Author in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, it is not unworthy of remark, that tho' the King hath taken upon him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with the <hi>Teſts,</hi> and to prohibit the requiring them; yet the Diſſenters, who have ſince that time, been preferred to publick Truſts, continue ſtill to take them, and go to the reſpective Courts, where by Law the Declaration is enjoined to be exacted, and there demand the being admitted to make it. Tho' in the mean ſeaſon they cannot be unſenſible, that it is the thing in the World whereby they moſt highly offend his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; it being both a proclaiming the Illegality of that Authority which he challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of diſpenſing with Laws; and a defeating, ſo far as lieth in them, his great deſign as well as artifice, for the introducing of Popery, which his Soul is ſo much in travel with. And were not this Author both a perſon of a moſt depraved Conſcience, and deſtitute of all common ſenſe, he would never have ſlandered <hi>Monſieur Fagel,</hi> and ſo egregiouſly perverted his plain meaning, as to tell us, that tho' he be a <hi>Hollander and a Non-conformiſt, yet he thanks God for the Teſt Laws, by which his Non-conforming Brethren in</hi> England, <hi>of what degree and quality ſoever they be, ſtand excluded from Publick Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For every one that will be ſo kind to himſelf, and ſo juſt to the <hi>Penſionary,</hi> as to read his Letter, will immediately diſcern that there is not one word in it, upon which to ſuperſtruct this calumny and accuſation; ſeeing he therein affirms in repeated and emphatical Terms, that all contained in, and deſigned by the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws, is <hi>the ſecuring the Reformed Religion, thro' the having provided, that none be allowed to ſit in Parliament, nor admitted to Publick Offices, except they declare that they are of the Reformed, and not of the Roman Catholick Religion.</hi> So that how <hi>Monſieur Fagel's Non-conformity Brethren in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſhould come to be affected by theſe Laws ſo as to receive any prejudice by them, is that which none but a perſon of our Author's wit, integrity and candor, could have had the faculty either to conceive or alledge.</p>
            <pb n="347" facs="tcp:40747:3"/>
            <p>But that we may come to the <hi>ſecond particular;</hi> there is the leſs reaſon to wonder at this Gentleman's calumniating <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel,</hi> and affixing dull, tho' malicious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries of his own unto him, if we do but conſider with what petulancy and injuſtice he treats Their <hi>Serene Highneſſes,</hi> and at the gate of their own Court aſſumeth the confidence to miſrepreſent, leſſen and aſperſe them. The nearneſs which thoſe Princes ſtand in to the aſcending the Engliſh Throne, and the joyful proſpect which all Proteſtants have of it, exciteth a diſcontent and rage in our Author, which he knows not how either to ſuppreſs or govern. For not to mention what we learn of the kindneſs of Roman Catholicks to an Heir, profeſſing the Reformed Religion, from the proceedings of <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> and the Papiſts in <hi>France</hi> towards <hi>Henry</hi> 4. we are ſufficiently inſtructed what good will they bear to a Proteſtant Succeſſor, by the Bull which <hi>Clement</hi> 8. publiſhed about the End of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign. For the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream and Infallible Head does therein ordain, <hi>That when it ſhould happen to that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Woman to die, they ſhould admit none to the Crown, quantumque propinquitate ſanguinis niterentur, niſi ejuſmodi eſſent qui fidem Catholicam non modo tolerarent, ſed omni ope ac ſtudio promoverent, &amp; more majorum jurejurando ſe id praeſtituros ſuſciperent; whatſoever Right and Title they ſhould have thereunto, by vertue of their next affinity in blood, unleſs they ſhould firſt ſwear not only to tolerate, but to advance and eſtabliſh the Romiſh Religion.</hi> Nor can I avoid being filled with fear and reverence to the ſafety of ſome certain perſons, when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> commends <hi>Irene</hi> for murdering the Emperor her Son, becauſe he was againſt the Worſhip of Images, and not only calls it <hi>Juſtitiae zelum, a righteous zeal</hi> but adds, <hi>Chriſtum docuiſſe, ſummum pietatis genus eſſe in hoc adverſus filium eſſe fidelem, That Chriſt hath taught the perfiction of Religion in ſuch a caſe to conſiſt in fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the Church, tho' by deſtroying one that was both her Son and her Soveraign.</hi> 'Tis a high piece of injuſtice in our Author towards Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> and calculated for no other end but to alienate his Majeſties affections from them, when he tells us, that <hi>the thing aimed at in the writing of the Penſionary's Letter, as well as that purſued in the manner of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing it, was to obſtruct the King's righteous &amp; pious deſigns, and to render them unpracticable.</hi> For the Letter being written in obedience to the Command of Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> &amp; to declare their Opinion in reference to the ſeveral matters, about which it treateth; it plainly follows that tho' <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> be accountable for the manner of cloathing and delivering their thoughts, and for the Order and Method in which things are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, and poſſibly for the ratiocinations by which they are ſupported and enforced, yet that the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> are the perſons who are alone reſponſible for the End unto which it was intended. And it appears to have been ſo far from their intentions, thereby to obſtruct and defeat any pious and juſt deſigns of his Majeſty; that nothing can be more viſible, than that as it is admirably adapted to the giving eaſe and ſecurity to all his Proteſtant Subjects, ſo it offereth means for relieving the Papiſts from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Laws to which they are liable, and for the granting them a Warranty in a legal way for the exerciſe of their Religion. Nor doth it diſcourage any kind of favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, ſave that which the conceſſion whereof, would not only be inconſiſtent with the peace and ſafety of thoſe of the Reformed Religion in <hi>England,</hi> but which might enflame the Nation to ſuch Reſentments, as would in all likelihood both endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger his Majeſties Perſon and Crown, and come at laſt to iſſue in the reducement of the Roman Catholicks to worſe circumſtances, than they have hitherto been acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with. But to proceed with our Author, to whom it is ſo natural to act fooliſhly, and with ſaucineſs and injuſtice, that neither the Character he is ſaid to bear, nor the Quality of the Perſons of whom he ſpeaks, can either reſtrain his intemperance, or correct his rudeneſs and indiſcretion. For <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi> having ſaid, that he believes there are many Roman Catholicks, who under the preſent ſtate of Affairs, will not be very deſirous to be in Publick Offices and Employments, nor uſe any attempts againſt thoſe of the Reformed Religion; and that not only becauſe they know it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, but leſt it ſhould at ſome other time, prove prejudicial to their Perſons and States. Our Author is ſo unjuſt as well as imprudent, as to call this <hi>a menacing not only of all the Non-conformiſts and Roman Catholicks in</hi> England, <hi>but a threatning of his Majeſty, and an inſulting over him:</hi> And from thence he takes occaſion to add, <hi>that he hopes God will inable his Majeſty to repreſs and prevent the effects of theſe menaces, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him with means of mortifying thoſe who do thus threaten and inſult over him.</hi> It certainly argues a ſtrange weakneſs and diſtemper of mind, to call ſo modeſt and ſoft an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both a <hi>menacing of the King and of all his Catholick Subjects,</hi> when I dare ſay, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth the ſenſe of all among the Papiſts who are endowed with any meaſure of Wiſdom, and is nothing elſe ſave a Declaration of the meaſure, by which they do at this day regulate and conduct themſelves. But the injuſtice of our Author towards Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> in his Reflections upon the forementioned expreſſion of the <hi>Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary's,</hi>
               <pb n="348" facs="tcp:40747:4"/>is his intending them by the perſons that do threaten his Majeſty and inſult o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him. For did he take <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> for the only guilty perſon in reference to this Phraſe which he miſcalls a <hi>Menace,</hi> it would be a ſtrange detracting in him from the Power and Glory of his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> to wiſh him ſufficient means whereby to ſhun the effects of a Gentleman's threatning, whoſe higheſt Figure in the World is meerly to be a Miniſter in a Republick. Nor would he bring down his Maſter to ſo low a level, as to make it the higheſt Object of his Hopes, concerning ſo great a Monarch, that he ſhall be able to <hi>mortifie</hi> a perſon, who whatſoever his Merit be, yet his Fortune is to fill no ſublimer a <hi>Poſt.</hi> So that it can be no other ſave the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs,</hi> whom our Author in his uſual way of injuſtice, petulancy and indiſcretion does here character, repreſent and intend. And what he thereupon means by the <hi>Kings having power in his hands, and by his hoping that God would furniſh him with means by which he may mortifie them,</hi> is not a matter of difficult penetration, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by perſons of the moſt ordinary capacities. For the ſeveral methods that have been projected, and are ſtill carrying on, for the debarring them from the Succeſſion to the Imperial Crowns of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to which they have ſo Juſt and Hereditary a Right, are ſufficient to detect unto us what our Author intends, and ſerve as a Key whereby to open the ſcope, and meaning of his Expreſſions. But whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Papal and Jeſuitick Endeavours may be, for the obſtructing and preventing their Aſcending the Thrones of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> I dare ſay that all the effects they will have, will be only the diſcovering the folly and malice of thoſe that attempt it, and that they can never be able to compaſs and accompliſh it. For as their Highneſſes have both that intereſt in the Love and Veneration of all Proteſtants, and ſo indiſputable a Title, that it is impoſſible they ſhould be precluded either by <hi>Force,</hi> or in a way to which their Enemies may affix the Name of <hi>Legal;</hi> ſo there is no great cauſe to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend or fear, their being ſupplanted by the King's having Male Iſſue of a vigour to live, conſidering both his Majeſties condition and the Queens, which is ſuch that they can never communicate <hi>bona ſtamina vitae.</hi> And for the Papiſts being able to <hi>Banter</hi> a ſuppoſitious Brat upon the Nation, (tho' there are many among them villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous enough to attempt it) we have not only the watchfulneſs of Divine Providence to rely upon for preventing it, but there are many faithful and waking Eyes that will be ready and induſtrious to diſcover the Cheat. And if the People once perceive, that there hath been a contrivance carried on for putting ſo baſe an affront upon a noble and generous Kingdom, and of committing ſo horrid a wrong againſt ſuch Vertuous and Excellent Princes; I donot know but that their Reſentment of it may riſe ſo high, as that all who are diſcovered to have been acceſſory unto it, may undergo the like fate that they of old did, who were found to have been conſcious and contributory unto the thruſting the Eunuch <hi>Smerdis</hi> into the <hi>Perſian</hi> Throne. Nor do I in the leaſt doubt but that the ſame Righteous, Wiſe and Merciful God, who prevented the like villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny when deſigned in the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and which was advanced ſo far, that ſome Prieſts had the wickedneſs and impudence, both to give thanks in the publick Churches for her Majeſties ſafe delivery of a Prince, and alſo to deſcribe the Beauty and Features of the <hi>Babe,</hi> tho' all ſhe had gone with amounted only to a <hi>Tympany</hi> of Wind and Water; I ſay that I do not queſtion, but that the ſame God will out of his Immenſe Grace and Sapience, find ways and methods, of which there are many within the compaſs of his Infinite Underſtanding, by which ſo helliſh a piece of villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if there be any ſuch projected and promoting, may be brought into light and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed. And truly when I conſider the Chriſtian and Royal Vertues wherewith their Highneſſes are imbued, and how they are furniſhed, with all the Moral, Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual and Religious accompliſhments, that are requiſite for adapting them to weild Scepters, and which render them not only ſo agreeable to the neceſſities and deſires of all good people, but ſo admirably qualified to anſwer both the preſent poſture of Affairs in <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Exigencies of thoſe that are oppreſſed and afflicted; I grow into a confidence, that as the Church of God both in <hi>Brittain</hi> and elſewhere, and the circumſtances in which ſo many Countreys are involved, do beſpeak and crave their Exaltation to the Thrones of the Brittiſh Dominions, ſo that they are both deſtined of God unto them, and will in due time be ſafely conducted thither. Nor can I avoid pleaſing my ſelf with thoſe joyful and hopeful thoughts, when I reflect upon the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſteps of Divine Providence, by which they are brought into that nearneſs of legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inheriting theſe Crowns. Certainly there is a voice that ſpeaketh loud to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not only in Gods denying a Legitimate Iſſue to the Late King, and in his taking away from time to time all the Lawful Male Off-ſpring of his preſent Majeſty, but in the uniting their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> in Marriage, even to the croſſing a certain Perſons Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, whom I forbear to Name, as well as to the diſguſting of a Neighbouring Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,
<pb n="349" facs="tcp:40747:4"/>and to the defeating the buſie endeavours of the Popiſh Party. But I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our Author, whoſe Injuſtice to their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> and his malice againſt their Honour, Intereſt and Reputation, knows neither end nor bounds. For upon <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Fagel</hi>'s having ask'd, Who would go about to adviſe him or any man elſe, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> whom God has ſo far honoured, as to make them. Defenders of his Church, to approve and promote things ſo dangerous and hurtful both to the Reformed Religion, and to the publick ſafety, as the Repealing of the <hi>Test</hi> Laws would be; our Author does hereupon, with his wonted Friendſhip, Equity, and Candor to thoſe Excellent <hi>Princes,</hi> tells us that <hi>he hath not met with ſo bold a Declaration as this of calling them the Protectors of Gods Church, and that the aſcribing it to them, is a detracting from the Honour of Kings and Monarchs, who will not Abdicate from themſelves to any other ſo glorious a Title.</hi> And in purſuance of his rancour towards their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> he runs out in his way of Wit and Learning into a moſt ſilly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Diſcourſe about the Nature of a Church, and accuſeth the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> as if by having this Character conferred upon them, they had a deſign to uſurp from his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> the ſtile of Defenders of the Faith, and to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to themſelves <hi>the being the Protectors of the Church of</hi> England. Surely this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman does by vertue of his Popiſh Zeal and Iriſh Underſtanding, believe that no Titles are due to Princes in reference to the Church of God, but what are derived from the Papal Chair. Whereas I dare ſay, that <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi> in beſtowing this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle upon Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> did not dream of the Roman <hi>Pontif,</hi> but had been taught it by God Almighty, whom I take to be the Supream and true Fountain of Honour, who is pleaſed to character ſuch Princes as do cheriſh and favour his Church, by the Name of <hi>Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers,</hi> which is the term that the <hi>Penſionary</hi> uſeth in reference to their <hi>Highneſſes.</hi> And as it is their own merit, which according to the Tenor of the Divine Creation, hath entitled them to this glorious ſtile; ſo they are neither to be ridicul'd nor hectored out of that duty, of countenancing and ſupporting the Reformed Religion, nor to be deterred by bold and empty words from thoſe compaſſionate, generous, and Princely Offices to ſincere Orthodox Believers, by which they have deſerved it. And while others glory in the enjoyment of the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of moſt Chriſtian and moſt Catholick Kings, which their Vaſſalage to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> their contributing to the Exaltation of the Triple Crown, and their being the Popes Executioners in the ſhedding the Blood of Saints, hath procured unto them, 'tis enough for their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> to be by the Suffrage of all true Proteſtants, and that agreeably to the Doctrine and Authority of the Sacred Scriptures, had in eſteem, and reverenced for <hi>Nutritii</hi> and Protectors of Gods Church. Nor do they appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate this ſtile to themſelves, tho' they account it the brighteſt among all their Titles, but they acknowledge it to belong equally to many others, and are afflicted at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than that all Potentates may not juſtly claim a ſhare in it. And as the <hi>Penſionary</hi>'s aſcribing it unto their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> was out of no deſign to uſurp upon the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Title of Defender of the Faith, nor to affix any Authority unto them over that Church, ſo it will be no preſumption to add, that all of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in that Kingdom, how much ſoever differing in little and circumſtantial things among themſelves, are yet ſo far ſenſible of the obligations they are under to Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> and of the benefits they have all the Aſſurance to expect from them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that without meaning ill either to the King or to any one elſe, they will unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly join in ſtiling them Defenders of the Chriſtian Reformed Faith, and Protectors of Gods Church profeſſing the Proteſtant Religion. And they will eaſily know with whom they are to be angry, and againſt whom to direct their Reſentments. <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> had ſaid, that if the Diſſenters cannot during his Majeſties Reign be eaſed from the Penal Laws, unleſs the Teſts be alſo abrogated, that this will be an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs unto them, but for which the Roman Catholicks are only to be blamed, who chuſe rather to be contented, that they and their Poſterity ſhould remain ſtill obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Penal Laws, and expoſed to the hatred of the whole Nation, than be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from a capacity of attempting any thing againſt the peace and ſecurity of the Reformed Religion. Our Author whoſe envy and injuſtice againſt Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> is not yet fully ſpent, doth in his imprudent and indiſcreet way obtrude from hence upon the World, that <hi>the Nonconformiſts as well as the Roman Catholicks may hereby ſee where their true Intereſt ſtands, and that they are extreamly obliged to thoſe in whoſe Name this advice is given, for the Conſolation afforded them in the condition under which they are ſtated by Law.</hi> Which is as much as if he ſhould harangue the Nonconformiſts into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment againſt the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs,</hi> by aſſuring them that they are to hope for no relief againſt the Penal Laws by any favour of theirs. Whereas the Diſſenters are not only told that their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> are willing to conſent, but that they do fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove,
<pb n="350" facs="tcp:40747:5"/>that they ſhould have an entire Liberty for the full exerciſe of their Religion, without being obnoxious to receive any prejudice, trouble, or moleſtation upon that account. So that the heat which our Author would enflame the Diſſenters unto againſt their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> ought to turn and ſpend it ſelf againſt the Papiſts, who rather than part with the <hi>Teſts</hi> which the Nonconformiſts are as much concerned to have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as they of the National Communion can be, are reſolved to keep all the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws in force, and to leave the Diſſenters under the dread and apprehenſion of them. But this they may be fully perſwaded of, that if they can eſcape the edge of them during this Kings Reign, they will be in no danger from them, in caſe the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come once to be ſo happy as to ſee their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> ſeated on the Throne. For as much as they have not only their word, which was hitherto never violated, laid to pledge for their relief and eaſe, but in that their Intereſt as well as their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will oblige them to be compaſſionate and tender to all ſorts of Proteſtants, and if they cannot be ſo Fortunate as to unite them, yet to exerciſe equal kindneſs and favour towards them.</p>
            <p>Having examined what our Author in his impertinent way venteth in unjuſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections againſt their <hi>Highneſſes;</hi> and having in ſome meaſure chaſtned him for them, tho' not to the Degree he does deſerve; I come now in the <hi>third place</hi> to call him to an account for his calumniating the States of theſe Provinces, and for his endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to poſſeſs the minds of their Popiſh Subjects with disſatisfaction and prejudice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. And if he be the perſon whom moſt men take him for, tho' he may have herein acted ſuitably to himſelf, yet he hath behaved diſagreeably to his chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, and unworthy of the <hi>Post,</hi> which his Maſter hath placed him in. Nor need we from henceforth to doubt, but that he does all the ill Offices he can between his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> and this Government, ſeeing he hath by ſlanders deſtitute of all Foundation, moſt maliciouſly ſtudied to raiſe differences betwixt them and their own Subjects. And if the Intelligence which he tranſmits to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> be as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually diſtant from truth and ſincerity, as the <hi>Memoirs</hi> are which he hath here publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we may eaſily conjecture what little credit ought to be given unto it, tho' at the ſame time we cannot but diſcern the end that it muſt be ſhapen and deſigned unto. Nor was there the leaſt occaſion adminiſtred by <hi>mijn Heer Fagel</hi> in his <hi>Letter,</hi> by which our Author could be provoked to attack theſe <hi>States,</hi> with ſo much rudeneſs, injuſtice, and falſhood, as he hath done in his <hi>Anſwer.</hi> For all that the <hi>Penſionary</hi> had ſaid, and which it ſeems threw our Author into a raging fit, was only that their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> could conſent that the Papiſts in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould be ſuffered to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their Religion with as much freedom, as is allowed them in theſe Provinces, in which they enjoy a full liberty of Conſcience. And as the time hath been, and may hereafter come, wherein the Engliſh Roman Catholicks would have thought, and may again account ſuch a Liberty for a happineſs; ſo I do not underſtand if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Roman Catholicks in theſe Countreys, be as our Author deſcribes it, with what conſiſtency either to Reaſon or with themſelves, the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> ſhould have ſo often heretofore in their <hi>Pleas</hi> for a Toleration, have made the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vouchſafed their Brethren in theſe Provinces, not only a motive for their own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of Indulgence, but to have repreſented it as the largeſt meaſure of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom they deſired, and which they would have been thankful for. Seeing this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman according to his accuſtomed manner of truth and ingenuity takes upon him to aſſure us, <hi>That as there can be no greater perſecution, than what the Papists undergo in the exerciſe of their Religion, in</hi> Guelderland, Freeſland, Zeland, <hi>and the Province of</hi> Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningue; <hi>ſo that the Liberty which they even enjoy in</hi> Holland, <hi>is ſo mean and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that it doth not deliver them from being ſubject to daily fines and moleſtations.</hi> Surely this man is either very unacquainted with what is done upon the account of Religion in other parts of the World, or elſe he muſt needs think, that the moſt brutal ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities to ſome, are Acts of Merit; while gentle reſtrictions upon others, are mortal Crimes, otherwiſe he could never write at this ignorant and extravagant rate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all perſons muſt diſcern his folly as well as inſincerity and neglect of truth. For we have too many deplorable evidences daily before our Eyes, beſides thoſe which arrive with us by reports of unqueſtionable credit, of a ſtranger kind of <hi>Perſecution</hi> exerciſed towards thoſe of the Reformed Religion in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> than any which the Roman Catholicks in theſe Provinces can be alledged to be under, except it be by one of our Author's veracity and diſcretion. Neither needs there any other Refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the calumny with which he aſperſeth the Supream and Subordinate Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of this Country in reference to the treating their Popiſh Subjects with horrid Severities, nor a clearer proof that thoſe of the Romiſh Communion, do eſteem them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be in a condition of peace, freedom and eaſe under this Government, than
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:40747:5"/>that of their behaviour during the late War carried on by the <hi>French</hi> King againſt theſe States, which he gave out both at <hi>Rome</hi> and at ſeveral other Courts in <hi>Europe,</hi> to have been undertaken in favour, and for the reſtoring of the Roman Catholick Religion. For had they lain under that grievous perſecution, and thoſe tragical hardſhips in the practice of it, which our Author would impoſe the belief of upon the World; they would not have failed to welcome that Monarch as their happy Deliverer, and would have united in a general Inſurrection againſt the States, for their having been Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous over them. But inſtead of that, moſt of them acquitted themſelves with the ſame Zeal for the ſupport of this Government, and in defence of their Country, that other Subjects did. Which demonſtrates beyond all controul, that they do not judge themſelves to be in ſo wretched and miſerable circumſtances, as this bold and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Perſon repreſents them to be. And whereas <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi> in juſtification of the neceſſity of preverving the <hi>Teſt Laws</hi> by which the Papiſts are precluded from Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Places of Truſt, and to rectifie a miſtake in Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi> about his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Roman Catholicks to continue capable of bearing publick Offices in this Commonwealth, had ſaid, that by the Laws of this Republick they are expreſly ſhut out from all the Employments both of Policy and Juſtice. Our Author does hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the higheſt Injuſtice, and with all the acrimony he can, accuſe the States, not only <hi>of departing from the expreſs Terms of the Pacification of</hi> Gant, <hi>but of violating the Articles of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion at</hi> Utrecht, <hi>which was the Foundation upon which this Government was both originally erected and doth ſtill ſubſiſt.</hi> And with his wonted degree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prudence he further adds, <hi>That the Provinces, and moſt of the Cities, would not have entred into the foreſaid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, but upon condition that they of the Roman Catholick Religion ſhould at all times poſſeſs the Government. And particularly that</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>had it ſtipulated unto them, under the Guaranty of the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>that none of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion ſhould be allowed a Place to aſſemble in, either within the Walls, or without, ſo far as the Juriſdiction of the City did extend.</hi> One would have little expected, that a perſon living in the Communion of the Romiſh Church, as our Author profeſſeth himſelf to do, ſhould upbraid theſe States with the violation of Articles, relating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Grant made unto any for their Security in the free Exerciſe of their Religion, at a ſeaſon when Popiſh Soveraigns not only account it their glory to break all Laws, Oaths and Edicts, by which Proteſtants had their Religion, together with many other Rights and Priviledges, eſtabliſhed and confirmed unto them, but who with a ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vageneſs and barbarity which ſcarce any Age can parallel, ſeek to extirpate their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and deſtroy them. And all this attempted and purſued againſt them, not only without their being guilty of any crime, by which they might have deſerved to loſe the favour of their Princes, and to forfeit protection in the free exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and their ſafety as to their Perſons and Eſtates, which had been ſworn unto them, and ſecured by Authentick Laws: But when one of the chiefeſt motives unto it, was their Loyalty, and the Merit that they had laid upon their reſpective Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, which by a new way of gratitude was thought fit to be thus recompenſed and rewarded. And if we be not, as I have formerly ſaid, ſtrangely deceived in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Character of our Author, this charge upon the States of theſe Provinces, is the effect of a moſt prodigious folly, as well as of inveterate malice, in that his Maſter contrary both to the Laws of the Realms, his often repeated Promiſes, and his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oath, aſſumes a power of introducing thoſe into Offices, who by the Statutes of the Land ſtand precluded from them, and of thruſting them out, who alone are the Perſons that are legally capable of them. Which manner of proceeding in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, hath beſides the injuſtice that attends it towards all that are laid aſide, a ſignal piece of ingratitude accompanying it to many of them, as having been the Perſons, whoſe Zeal for his Perſon brought him to the Throne, and whoſe courage maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in it. But I ſhall not think it enough meerly to have expoſed his imprudence and indiſcretion in the forementioned accuſation againſt the whole Governing Body of this Country; but I ſhall likewiſe ſhew it to be falſe, ſlanderous, and unjuſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part and branch of it. And that I may act with more truth and candour than our Author hath done, I do acknowledge, that at the firſt commencement of the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for the defence of the Laws and Priviledges of theſe and the neighbouring Provinces, that not only they of the Reformed Religion, but likewiſe the Roman Catholicks, took Arms and hazarded their Lives and Eſtates in that juſt quarrel. And I do alſo grant that thereupon there was Liberty of Conſcience allowed and eſtabliſhed by ſeveral Treaties, in the vertue of which, both parties were to be equally tolerated, and the one not to diſturb or diſquiet the other. Nor was there ever any thing done by way of Ordinance or Law, to leſſen or reſtrain the liberty of the Papiſts, nor to abridge, much leſs deprive them, of any Power, Juriſdiction and
<pb n="352" facs="tcp:40747:6"/>Authority that they poſſeſſed, ſo long as they remained faithful in the common cauſe, and behaved themſelves with Equity, Juſtice and Peace towards thoſe who had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from the Roman Communion. But ſuch was the aſcendency of the Prieſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Roman Catholicks, and ſo powerful was their influence upon them, that in a little time they not only hindred and moleſted the Proteſtants in the exerciſe of their Religion, and committed many unjuſt and cruel ſeverities againſt them, but they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to various attempts of betraying the Rights and Civil Liberties of the whole Country, and of enſlaving it both to the Tyranny of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to the bloudy and cruel Inquiſition. So that from hence it became a matter of neceſſity ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than at firſt of choice, that the Government ſhould be diſpoſed into Proteſtant hands; and that the liberty of the Papiſts, ſhould have thoſe limits and regulations given unto it, as might render it both conſiſtent with the peace, freedom, and ſafety of thoſe of the Reformed Religion, and with the preſervation of the Civil Rights and Priviledges of theſe Provinces. This is the account, which all who have written with any knowledge and integrity of the Tranſactions of thoſe Times, do give us of the many Changes and Revolutions that fell out in reference to Religion, till all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters both concerning it, and the Political Government of theſe Countreys came to be eſtabliſhed in the Form and Way, wherein they do ſtill continue and ſubſiſt. And this I do undertake to make good by all publick, Authentick, and approved Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, if our Author ſhall have the confidence to inſiſt upon the juſtification of his cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, And all that I ſhall at preſent direct men unto for the confirmation of what I have ſaid, is that admirable <hi>Apology</hi> of <hi>William</hi> I. Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whom his preſent <hi>Highneſs,</hi> does in Wiſdom, Steddineſs, and true temperate Chriſtian Zeal ſo ſignally imitate, and which that great Prince, who was the firſt and happy Founder of this Republick, publiſhed in defence of himſelf, and of thoſe actings, for which the ſlaviſh and mercenary Factors of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> had traduced and aſperſed him. But let us advance to a particular Examination of thoſe matters of Fact, upon which our Author challengeth theſe States <hi>for violating their Faith</hi> with their <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Subjects.</hi> And the things he is pleaſed to ſpecifie, <hi>are their departing from the Terms of the Pacification of</hi> Gant, <hi>and their breaking the Articles of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion agreed unto at</hi> U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht, 1597. Nor am I unwilling to acknowledge, that ſoon after the <hi>Pacification</hi> concluded at <hi>Gant,</hi> there were ſeveral indecent and undiſcreet things done contrary to the purport and tendency of it, both by thoſe of the Romiſh, and by them of the Reformed Religion. Which proceeded from the Superſtitious Fury of the former, and the imprudent Zeal of the latter. Yet it is certain, that the ground of its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be rendred wholly ineffectual, aroſe from a deſign of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cloak and palliation of that Treaty, to ſubvert the Civil Rights and Priviledges of all the Provinces, to the Defence and Preſervation of which the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks as well as Proteſtants were ſworn and bound by the ſaid <hi>Pacification.</hi> For after that <hi>Philip</hi> II. had in compliance with the neceſſity of his Affairs, conſented unto, and ratified all the Terms, Proviſions and Conditions, which both the Papiſts and the Reformed had in that <hi>Pacification,</hi> League and Confederacy, inſiſted upon, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to adhere unto; it was ſoon after diſcovered by Letters intercepted to <hi>Don John,</hi> who was at that time conſtituted Governour over the Low Countreys, that all which <hi>Philip</hi> aim'd at, was thro the having rendred them ſecure by the Ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Treaty, to take advantages whereby to enſlave them, and under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert of it, to provide himſelf of means, by which he might be eſtabliſhed in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Tyranny over them. So that by reaſon of what was detected in thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and from <hi>Don John</hi>'s proceeding to poſſeſs himſelf of <hi>Namur,</hi> and his endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to corrupt and debauch the German Troops, which were in the States ſervice, and paid by them, together with the defection of many of the Roman Catholicks from all the Terms of that Pacification; the War came again to be revived againſt the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all that had been agreed unto at <hi>Gant,</hi> was rendred ineffectual and overthrown. And I would fain know of our Learned and Wiſe Author, how the States of the <hi>Seven</hi> Provinces are more guilty of the violation of that <hi>Pacification,</hi> by making the Proteſtant Religion, to be that of the publick Eſtabliſhment, within their Territories and Juriſdiction; than the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the States of the <hi>Spaniſh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> are in their denying a Toleration of the Proteſtant Religion in thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; ſeeing I am ſure it was agreed and ſworn unto in that <hi>Pacification.</hi> And as for the Union concluded at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> the Terms whereof our Author upbraids theſe States with a departure from: It will be no difficult matter to ſhew how his knowledge and ſincerity are in reference to this particular of one meaſure and piece. For tho' diverſe of the Provinces, which entred into that Union, did thereby enjoy a Liberty of chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and determining which of the two Religions ſhould have the ſtamp of the publick
<pb n="353" facs="tcp:40747:6"/>eſtabliſhment within their own Juriſdictions; yet it was then and there ordained, that the Proteſtant Religion alone ſhould be publickly profeſſed, and have the protection of the Laws in the Provinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand.</hi> And as the other Provinces were left to do, as they ſhould judge beſt for the peace and ſafety of their reſpective Territories, and the ſupport and defence of the Union; ſo it is a thing wherein all that have written with any integrity, do agree, that the alterations which were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards made in theſe Provinces, or in reference unto them, concerning Religion, were either reſolved and decreed in the Provincial Aſſemblies of the States of thoſe ſeveral Provinces, or elſe in the meetings of the States-General, where not only the Deputies of thoſe ſeveral Provinces were preſent and conſenting, but behoved to have the approbation of their Principals, in order to the rendring thoſe Alterations le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and binding. Nor is it unworthy to be obſerved, that the chief occaſion for ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Roman Catholicks out of the Government, and for depreſſing the Romiſh Religion from being Dominant, aroſe from the Papiſts themſelves, in that not only contrary to their ſtipulations and promiſes, they were found in the vertue of a malice imbib'd from their Religion, to be upon all occaſions committing violences and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages againſt the Reformed, but in that the Roman Catholick Magiſtrates, and many others of that Communion, were diſcovered to retain too great an inclination to <hi>Spain,</hi> and to be ready to abandon and betray the Freedom and Civil Rights of their Countrey, inſtead of continuing ſtedfaſt and faithful in the defence of them, as they had covenanted and ſworn. In a word, as neither the Articles of the Union at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> nor any other Terms agreed upon, before the Abdication of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> which was not until <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. can be called the Fundamental Laws of the Government of this Republick, tho' they may be ſtiled conditions upon which ſuch and ſuch Provinces Aſſociated for mutual defence againſt the Spaniſh Power and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; ſo it is undeniable, that by reaſon of the many dangers they found themſelves expoſed unto, and the hazards they had run of being betrayed again into the hands of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> through their having ſuffered the Magiſtracy to remain any wherein Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and thro' their having allowed the Roman Catholick Religion to be publickly preached and exerciſed, they thereupon re-aſſumed and gave a new frame unto their Union in the Year 1583. in which it was agreed and enacted by all the Provinces, that from that time forward, the Reformed Religion ſhould alone be openly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and preached, and that none but Proteſtants ſhould from that time be admitted to any Office of Policy and Juſtice in the Government. And as this is the true Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Law upon which this State hath ſince ſo happily ſubſiſted and flouriſhed; ſo there can be nothing objected againſt the Juſtice of it, but what will lye againſt all States of the World, who have always changed and moulded their Laws, as they have been neceſſitated in order to ſelf-preſervation. And ſo remote from all truth, is our Author's affirming the Roman Catholicks to have been upon theſe Alterations brought under Perſecution; that Sir <hi>William Temple,</hi> whom the World will much ſooner believe than this Gentleman, tho' poſſibly he may bear the ſame character which that worthy perſon once did, does aſſure us in his excellent <hi>Obſervations upon the United Provinces of the</hi> Netherlands. That <hi>no Papiſt can here complain of being preſſed in his Conſcience, of being reſtrained from his own manner of Worſhip in his Houſe, or obliged to any other abroad, and that all ſuch, who ask no more than to ſerve God and ſave their own Souls, have as much Freedom, Eaſe and Security as they can deſire.</hi> Yea it is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Roman Catholicks enjoy advantages under this Government, which they have not in Popiſh States. In that being ſuffered to exerciſe their Religion ſo far as is neceſſary to attain all the ends of it, if it be capable of affording them any whereon they can hereafter find themſelves happy; they are delivered from the Tyranny of Prieſts over their Perſons and Eſtates, and hindred from being in a condition to do that ill to others, which the Doctrines of their Church would both tempt them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and juſtifie them in. And as to that which our Author ſays of the injuſtice done to the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and of the violating the Conditions towards the Roman Catholicks there, upon which under the guaranty of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> they came into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> he is miſtaken in that whole matter, and betrays only his ignorance, infidelity, or both. For the Conditions which he mentioneth, were the reſult of an Agreement made <hi>Anno</hi> 1578. when upon the <hi>Naſſovian</hi> Army's coming before their City to attack them, they abandoned the Party and Intereſt of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> whom they had till that time adhered unto, and came into an Alliance with the reſt of the Towns of the Province, to oppoſe him in defence of the Priviledges of theſe Countreys. And as this was a year before the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> concluded at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> into which <hi>Amſterdam</hi> entred at the ſame time that <hi>Gelderland, Zutphen, Holland, Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Utrecht</hi> did; ſo they joined in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> upon the ſame Terms, that the other Towns
<pb n="354" facs="tcp:40747:7"/>of their own Province had agreed unto. Nor could the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> be <hi>Guaranty</hi> in reference to the conditions ſpecified in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> foraſmuch as tho the Act of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was ſigned <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. 1579. yet the Prince did not ſign it till the <hi>May</hi> following. And that the Roman Catholick Magiſtrates, came to be diveſted of the Government, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Articles made with them when they forſook the party of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> they have none to blame for it but themſelves, nor was there that injuſtice in it which our Author does imagine. For not being ſatisfied to remain diſobedient and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory to an Edict and Decree of the Arch-Duke <hi>Matthias</hi> and the Council of State, who Anno 1578. had appointed, that whereſoever there were a hundred Families of thoſe profeſſing the Reformed Religion, that they ſhould there be allowed a Church or Chappel for the exerciſe of their Worſhip; they not only broke all their capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made with the Proteſtants, thro oppreſſing them in various, ſevere, unjuſt, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod's, and in denying them a decent and convenient place in which they might bury their dead, but they were found to be ſtill inclining to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intereſt, and ready to eſpouſe it upon the firſt convenient opportunity. And therefore the Proteſtants, who were by much the majority, partly to relieve themſelves from the ſufferings which were daily inflicted upon them contrary to ſtipulations and Articles, and partly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the miſchiefs which would have enſued to the whole Country, ſhould that City have been betrayed again into the power and hands of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> aſſumed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to themſelves, and eaſed the other party of the Truſt, which they had ſo unwiſely and unrighteouſly managed. Nor can our Author deny, but that ſince they took on them the Ruling Authority, they have exerciſed it with all the moderation that can be expreſſed. And have been ſo far from returning to the Roman Catholicks, the like meaſures which themſelves had met with, that they have in no one thing given them cauſe to complain, unleſs they ſhould quarrel that they are kept out of capacity of doing the miſchief, their prieſts would otherway's be ready to excite them unto, and which their Religion would countenance them in.</p>
            <p>But it is now time that I ſhould proceed to the <hi>fourth</hi> thing, for which I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call our <hi>Anonymous</hi> Anſwerer to an account. And were he not of a ſingular <hi>Forehead,</hi> and of a peculiar complexion from all others; he could not have had the impudence to endeavour to deceive the world into a belief, that the Proteſtant Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> ſtand liſted by their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> into the ſame rank with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and that they are hereafter to expect, to be ſhut up into the ſame ſtate and condition. Certainly he muſt either have an Antipathy woven into his nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all truth and ſincerity, or elſe thro having long accuſtomed himſelf to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reporting of perſons and to the giving falſe repreſentations of things, he muſt at laſt have acquired an incurable Habit, otherwiſe it were impoſſible to prevaricate to that degree from truth, in every thing he medleth with, and which he undertaketh to ſay. For <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> having declared, that the reaſon why their Highneſſes can not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to the Repeal of the Teſt Laws, is becauſe they are of no other tendency, than to ſecure the Reformed Religion from the deſigns of the Roman Catholicks, and that they contain only conditions and proviſions, whereby men may be qualified to be Members of Parliament, and to bear publick Offices. Our Author hereupon tells us. <hi>That the Nonconformiſts as well as the Roman Catholicks, do apprehend that they receive a great deal of damage, by thoſe Laws, and do account them extremely prejudicial to their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Families.</hi> And whereas <hi>Monſieur Fagel</hi> had ſaid, that he would be glad to hear one good Reaſon, whereby a Proteſtant fearing God, and concerned for his Religion, could be prevailed upon to conſent to the Repealing of theſe Laws which have been enacted by the Authority of King and Parliament, and that have no other tendency ſave the providing for the ſafety of the Reformed Religion, and the hindreing Roman Catholicks from being in a capacity to ſubvert it. Our Author in way of reflection upon this, tells us, that it is not only <hi>a Childiſh demand, but that it is to be hop'd that the penſionary will from hence be brought to acknowledg, how trifling and weak all thoſe Reaſons are, by which he would preclude the Nonconformiſts as well as the Roman Catholicks from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employments.</hi> So that by theſe and many other paſſages equally falſe and diſingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in our Author's pretended Anſwer, which for brevity's ſake I forbear to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is apparent that he endeavours to perſwade the world into a belief, that the Diſſenters are ſtated by their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> in the ſame rank and condition with the Papiſts, and are to expect to be treated in the ſame manner, in caſe it pleaſe the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to bring Their Highneſſes to the Throne. One would wonder at this ſudden and ſtrange change in the opinion and conduct of the Papiſts towards the Nonconformiſts; that they who were repreſented by them a while ago' as unfit to live in His Majeſties Dominions; ſhould now come to be accounted the Kings beſt and moſt Faithful Subjects, and worthy to be advanced to the chief Truſts and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy's.
<pb n="355" facs="tcp:40747:7"/>'Tis but a few years ſince, that all the Laws enacted againſt them, were judged to be too few and gentle, and therefore they had Laws executed upon them, to which the Legiſlators had never made them obnoxious; but now the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks are become ſo tender of their eaſe and ſafety, that out of pure kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto them, if any will be ſo fooliſh as to believe it, they muſt have Laws abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, which in the worſt times, and during the moſt illegal and barbarous proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures againſt them, they were never affected with nor ſuffered the leaſt prejudice by. And whereas it was the only way for perſons heretofore to make their Court at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, by declaiming againſt the Diſſenters as Rebels and Traitors, and by putting them into a ſalvage Dreſs, to be run upon as beaſts of prey; it is now grown the only method of becoming gracious at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> to proclaim their Loyalty, and to cry them up for the only people in whom his Majeſty, with ſafety to his Perſon and Crown, can repoſe a confidence. But under all the Shapes which the Papiſts do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, they may be eaſily diſcovered to retain the ſame malice to the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and only to act thoſe various and oppoſite parts, in order the better to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it. And the Diſſenters being haraſſed and oppreſſed before, and indulged and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed now, was upon the ſame motive of hatred unto it, and in ſubſerviency to its extirpation. The method's are altered, but the deſign is one, and tho they have chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Tools, yet they remain conſtant in the purſuance of the ſame End. While they of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were found compliant with the ways, which the Factors for <hi>Rome</hi> thought ſerviceable thereunto, they were not only the Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of the Court and of the whole Popiſh party, but were gratified, at leaſt as was pretended, with a rigorous execution of the Penal Laws upon Diſſenters. But there remaining ſeveral ſteps to be taken for the introduction of Popery, and the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Reformed Religion, which they of the National Communion would not go along with them in, they are forced to ſhift Inſtruments, and to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Nonconformiſts; whoſe aſſiſtance the better to engage, they have not only ſuſpended all the Penal Laws, to which the Diſſenters were liable, but have endeavoured to fill them with jealouſy and apprehenſion of danger from the Teſt Acts, tho at the ſame time they know that Nonconformiſts never either did, or could receive prejudice by them. Only they are ſenſible, that if they could work up that eaſie people into ſuch a belief, they ſhould thereby not only obtain their concurrence and abettment, for the reſcinding of thoſe Laws, that are at preſent the only great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Fence about our Religion, and upon the abrogation whereof nothing could hinder the Papiſts from getting into a condition to extirpate it; but make them a formed and united Body with themſelves againſt the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> who have with ſo much Wiſdom, Courage and Integrity, declared that they are againſt the having them repealed. And as the Diſſenters cannot have ſo far renounced all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard both to honeſty and to a good name, as to be fond of being herded with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or thank our Author for it; ſo they muſt be become void of all ſenſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, if they ſuffer themſelves to be either wheedled or frighted into an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their being ſubject to receive any dammage by the Teſts; it being ſo expreſly contrary both to the Terms of thoſe Laws, and to their own experience. Nor can they be ſo far abandoned of God, nor prove ſo treacherous to the Nation, Poſterity and the whole Proteſtant Intereſt thro' Europe, as to cooperate to the Repeal of them, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying that great Fence about the Reformed Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and to put the Papiſts into capacity both of ſubverting it there and every where elſe. And ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide a few mercenary fellows among them, there is no ground to fear, after we have had ſo many proofs of their zeal for the Proteſtant Religion and Engliſh Liberties, in the worſt of times and under the greateſt Temptations, that they ſhould at this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when all others behave themſelves with ſo much Integrity and Courage, be acceſſory to ſo villanous a thing. The ill ſucceſs which the Court hath met with in the ſeveral Towns and City's, ſince the late Regulation of the Corporations, ſufficiently ſhews, that the Diſſenters who were put into Magiſtracy, in hopes by them to have compaſſed the packing of a Parliament, are no leſs careful of preſerving the Teſt Laws, than they of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Communion were, who were diſplaced to make way for them. And to diſcover the groſsneſs of the abuſe, which our Author, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regard to Truth or Ingenuity, endeavours to put upon them, as if they were judged by their Highneſſes to be incapable of Truſts and Employments, or any ways concluded to ſtand under thoſe reſtraints by the Teſt, which the Roman Catholicks do; there is not one word in <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi>'s Letter, whereby they are ſaid to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto them, or by which there is any ground adminiſtred of fancying they are put into the ſame rank with the Papiſts, and whereby to fear that they may hereafter come to be treated accordingly. But in ſtead of this, they are expreſly told, that Their
<pb n="356" facs="tcp:40747:8"/>
               <hi>Highneſſes</hi> do both allow and deſire the abrogation of all the Penal Laws againſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and the having them freed from the ſeverity of them; and that they do not only conſent but heartily approve of their having an entire liberty granted them for the full exerciſe of their Religion, without any trouble or hindrance, or being left expoſed to the leaſt moleſtation or inconvenience upon that account. And to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie how far the Nonconformiſts are from being in the leaſt menaced by thoſe Laws, it is again Declared, that the only reaſon why their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> refuſe to conſent to the having them repealed, is, becauſe that they have no other tendency, ſave to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Reformed Religion from the Deſigns of the Papiſts, by containing provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the vertue of which, thoſe only may be kept out of Office who can not teſtifie that they are of the Reformed, and not of the Roman Catholick Religion. Which as it is the higheſt evidence imaginable, of their own ſtedfaſtneſs and integrity in the Reformed Religion, and of the compaſſion and love which they equally bear to all who profeſs it, and how careful they will at all times be to have it maintained and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; ſo it is the putting ſuch a merit upon all Proteſtants, that it ſhould engage their prayers for their happy extation to the Throne, and make them ambitious as well as willing and ready to hazard their lives and Fortunes, for the ſecuring the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion unto them, if any ſhould be ſo wicked as to go about to preclude them.</p>
            <p>But I muſt pay a further attendance upon our Author, and accompany him to the <hi>fifth</hi> particular which I promiſed to conſider; namely that according to his own fooliſh and incoherent way of writing, while he pretends to commend and juſtify the proceeding of His Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> he publiſheth the villany of the Papal Church, and proclaims the diſhonour and injuſtice of diverſe Eminent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs and Princes of the Romiſh Communion. His <hi>Panegyricks</hi> upon the King of <hi>England,</hi> are ſo many juſt <hi>Satyr's</hi> upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Savoy, &amp;c.</hi> For if it be <hi>becoming a Christian, to be of a contrary judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe who are for perſecuting ſuch as differ from the publick and eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and if it be a ſentiment worthy of a Royal mind, that none ought to be oppreſſed for their Conſciences in Divine Matters;</hi> what characters of irreligion, ignominy, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, are due unto them, who judge it to be meritorious to deſtroy ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for no other pretended Crime, ſave that they cannot believe as the Pope and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do. Surely our Author muſt either be extreamly ignorant of the Doctrine of his own Church, and of the bloody and barbarous practices purſuant thereunto, both at this day, and for many ages paſt; or elſe he muſt be the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincere miſcreant that ever writ, or at beſt be guilty of the inconſiſtency and folly as to continue in the Communion of a Church, whoſe Articles of Faith he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns as Antichriſtian, and whoſe practices according to the Terms made neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for Salvation, he abhorreth both as unworthy of Royal Minds, and contrary to Chriſtian Piety. But tho nothing can render a falſe man honeſt, or a fooliſh Man wiſe, yet ſeeing ſomething may be done towards the curing a perſon's ignorance if he be teachable, or at leaſt to ſhew his obſtinacy, and that the fault is in his will, not in his Underſtanding, if he will not learn and be convinced; I ſhall therefore both acquaint him a little with the Doctrine of that Church, and briefly put him in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, how theſe of the Romiſh Fellowſhip have therefore perſecuted Chriſtians, and ſtill continue ſo to do, only for differing from the publick and eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. As to the firſt, it is ſufficiently known that according to the judgment of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> we are Hereticks, and that Hereſie being <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis Divinae,</hi> we are therefore the worſt of Traitors, and liable to the Penalties of the greateſt High Treaſon. And thereupon we are not only declared to be infamous and ſentenced to be deprived of all Honor and Dignity, and to be incapable of all Offices, and have our Eſtates confiſcated and ſeiſed; but we are condemned to be burnt, and if that cannot conveniently be effected, it is both made lawful and meritorious to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate us by War or Maſſacre, as ſhall be beſt and moſt ſafe for the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In order whereunto, not only all Laws made for our Security are declared to be null, and that no promiſes made unto us, ought to be kept; but all Princes, that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to deſtroy and extirpate us, are proclaimed to be depoſed. And ſutable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto has their carriage been for many ages to ſuch as differ from them in Articles of Faith, and will not joyn in their Superſtitions and Idolatries. In proof whereof I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther need to inſiſt upon the infinite Murders, committed by the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> the moſt Deviliſh Engine of Cruelty that ever the World was acquainted with, nor to reflect ſo far backward as the <hi>Pariſian</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacres, or the infinite Slaughters perpetrated heretofore in <hi>France, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countreys, &amp;c.</hi> ſeeing we have ſuch freſh and doleful evidences of the mercy and gentleneſs of the Papal Church, in the ungrateful, inhumane, perjurious, and ſalvage perſecutions executed ſo lately
<pb n="357" facs="tcp:40747:8"/>in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piedmont. If it be the effect of Royal and Paternal affection in the King of</hi> England <hi>to his Subjects, that all he endeavoureth, is to treat them as becomes a common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without making any diſtinction between one and another,</hi> as our Author is pleaſed to call it in his Teſtimony concerning him; what cruel Parents muſt many Princes of the Roman Communion be, who act with that difference towards their people, that while they cheriſh and embrace ſome, they tear out the Bowels, and ſuck the blood of others? And if no Society deſtitute of ſuch tender and Chriſtian affections, can merit the name of a Church, we hence learn where to faſten the character of being the <hi>Mother of Harlots.</hi> In that we not only know whoſe Doctrine it is, that whom She cannot convert, She ought to deſtroy; but that we have obſerved her, to have been in all Ages <hi>drunk with the Blood of Saints.</hi> All the commendations our Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon the King of <hi>England;</hi> are not only either ſo many accuſations of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties inſincerity in the Papal Faith, or infallible indications that both the King (pardon the expreſſion) and his Miniſter, are Hypocritical Diſſemblers; but they are ſtabbing and twinging Satyr's againſt Mother Church, and the Holy Father, and againſt his Brittanick Majeſties dear Brother and Ally the <hi>French</hi> King. Nor can we be guilty either of Crime or Indecency, in the worſt we can ſay of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Moſt Chriſtian King; ſeeing we have in equivalent Terms a Preſident for it, both from ſo good a Catholick, and ſo wiſe a Miniſter of a great Monarch, as our honourable Author is.</p>
            <p>And tho I begin to grow weary of converſing with ſo impertinent a man, yet I am bound to wait upon him a little longer, and while the Reader can reap no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by any thing he ſays, to ſee whether it be not poſſible to lay hold of an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from his Ignorance and Folly, to communicate things that may be more ſolid and inſtructive. The <hi>ſixth</hi> thing therefore whereof I accuſed him, and for which I promiſed to call him to an account, is his egregious ignorance in relation to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Laws, Cuſtoms, and matters of Fact, <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws being enacted by King and Parliament for the Security of the Reformed Religion, and the Roman Catholicks receiving no prejudice by them, but being meerly reſtrained from getting into a condition to ſubvert it, therefore Their <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> could not conſent to their Repeal. And he further adds, that there is no Kingdom, Common-wealth, or any conſtituted Body and Society, in which there are not Laws made for the ſafety thereof, which not only provide againſt all attempts that may diſturb their peace, but which preſcribe ſuch conditions as they judge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for the diſcerning who are qualified to bear Employments. To which he again ſubjoins, that there is a great difference between the conduct of theſe of the Reformed Religion towards Roman Catholicks, which is moderate, and only to prevent their getting into a capacity to do hurt; and that of thoſe of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion towards the Reformed, who not being ſatisfied to exclude them from places of Truſt, do both ſuppreſs the whole Exerciſe of their Religion and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely perſecute all that profeſs it. And he finally adds, that both Reaſon and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the preſent, as well as paſt Ages do ſhew, that it is impoſſible for Roman Catholicks, and thoſe of the Reformed Religion, when joyned together in places of Truſt, and publick Employment, to maintain a good Correſpondence, live in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual peace, and to diſcharge their Offices quietly and to the publick Good. Now from theſe ſeveral paſſages, which carry their own evidence along with them, our Author takes occaſion both to vent his fooliſh and ridiculous Politicks, and to proclaim his ignorance in Hiſtory and of the moſt obvious matters of Fact. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we ſhall have the patience to hearken to what he hath been pleaſed to ſay, and ſhall examine it piece by piece, as we go along. And the firſt thing he does is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with a mighty Myſtery of State, and which none but ſo great a Miniſter could have been able to have revealed; namely, that tho <hi>the King and Parliament upon the firſt Revolution with reſpect to Religion, and the introducing and ſetting up the Reformed Religion, thought fit to make thoſe Laws which they judged neceſſary for its preſervation; yet that it does not follow that his preſent Majeſty and a Parliament would be of the ſame mind, but that they might enact Laws of a differing Nature from the former, and re-eſtabliſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into the ſame State, in which it was before the Reformed Doctrine and Worſhip was ſet up.</hi> We are much obliged to our Author for this diſcovery, though I muſt add, that this it is to truſt a Fool with ſecrets, for he will be ſure to be blabbing. For tho he ſubjoin, that he will not ſay that matters would be puſhed ſo far; yet he hath already told us enough, to make us underſtand both what his own hopes are, and what is deſigned by the Papal party, if they could compaſs a Parliament of a Complexion and Temper to their mind. But there are two fatal things, which lye in their way. One is, that neither progreſſing nor cloſeting, bribing nor threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="358" facs="tcp:40747:9"/>can prove effectual to give them the ſlendereſt ground of confidence of their obtaining a Parliament of that mould and conſtitution. And the ſecond is, that all the Members muſt take the Teſts, before they can be a Legal Parliament; and then there is little probability, that they who can make the Declaration required in theſe Laws, will be inclinable to Repeal them; eſpecially at a ſeaſon, when their own ſafety as well as that of the Proteſtant Religion, renders it ſo neceſſary to have them maintained. Whatſoever any Body of men, by what name ſoever they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or within what walls ſoever they aſſemble, ſhall attempt to do, without firſt having taken the Teſts; is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> null and void in Law, and will ſerve to no Legal purpoſe, but to make themſelves obnoxious to the ſevereſt puniſhments, which the Juſtice of a provoked and betrayed Nation can be able to inflict upon them. So that we do not doubt what the King would do, for the re-eſtabliſhing Popery and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Proteſtant Religion, could he get a Parliament to his mind; but our hope is that he will not, and the better to prevent it, we will endeavour to keep our Teſt Laws. But to go on with our Author, who with his accuſtomed ignorance, but perſonating here the wiſdom of a <hi>Solon</hi> or a <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> takes upon him to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, that <hi>as nothing can be called the fundamental Law of a Kingdom or a Republick, but what was enacted at the commencement of that State or Society, before any alterations could fall out in it with reference to Religion; ſo nothing deſerves the name of ſuch a Law ſave that which is to the advantage and benefit of all the Subjects.</hi> It were not amiſs here to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, by what Authority our Author faſtens on <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> this Term of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Law in reference to the Teſts; ſeeing he never uſed it in his Letter much leſs applyed it to ſuch a purpoſe. But falſifying is ſo natural to this Gentleman, that he could not avoid it, even when he might have been ſenſible, that he would not eſcape the being challenged for it. There is a Countrey in the world, that is ſaid to bear no poyſonous animal, nor had it need, ſeeing if any number of the Natives be of the mould and frame that ſome are, there are brutal and venemous Creatures enough in it, tho there be neither Toad nor Serpent there. But may not the Teſt Laws anſwer the end they were deſigned unto, of being a Fence about Religion, tho they be none of the Fundamental Laws of the Government. It is not the name that alone gives value to a Law; but the Sanction of the Legiſlative Authority, and the uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it to the publick good. A Statute, that was occaſioned by a neceſſity ariſng in reference to the publick Safety, ought as much to be ſtood by and upheld while that neceſſity continues, as if it were an original Law and Coaeval with the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if it was the indiſpenſable dependance of the Welfare and Safety of the Community upon ſuch and ſuch Proviſions at firſt, that gave them the Name of Fundamental Laws; I am ſure, that under our preſent Circumſtances, we may call the Teſt Laws abſolutely needful, if we aſſume not the vanity to ſtile them Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental. Beſides I would fain know of our Author, that if all Laws lye expoſed to an eaſie Abrogation, that are not coaeval with the Kingdom; what will then become of the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for Liberty of Conſcience, which his Majeſty not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, but undertakes to make irrepealable? And withal may not ſome Laws be as neceſſary to the being and preſervation of a State under the notion of Proteſtant; as others are to its being and ſubſiſtence under the conſideration of an embodied and formed Society? Every Society is bound to uſe all neceſſary means to preſerve it ſelf, and while it maketh no proviſions in order thereunto, that derive inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience upon others, unleſs it be only to keep them from being able to do hurt; it would be a wickedneſs as well as a folly to neglect them. In a word, as the making no Laws neceſſary for the Safety of a people under any knowledge of God they may be grown up into, but what were coaeval with their firſt formation into a Kingdom or Republick, were the weakning and undermining the Security of the Chriſtian Religion in all parts of the world where it hath obtained to be embraced and ſetled; ſo by the ſame reaſon that it is lawful to make proviſions for the preſervation of Chriſtianity in a State profeſſing the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; it is alſo lawful to make the like proviſions for the Security of the Reformed Religion in theſe Kingdoms and Common-wealths, which have judged it to be their duty to God, and their Souls, to receive and eſtabliſh it. And for our Author's ſaying, that no <hi>Law deſerves to be called Fundamental, ſave that which is to the benefit and advantage of all the Subjects;</hi> it is wholly impertinent to the caſe for which it is alledged, and does no way's attack or weaken what the <hi>Penſionary</hi> had ſaid. For as the Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for to be maintained, were never ſtiled Fundamental; ſo many thouſands may have benefit by a Law; whom nevertheleſs all perſons of ſenſe and wiſdom will account unfit to be advanced to publick Truſts. As no man will judge it unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to require that all who are held capable of publick employments, ſhould have
<pb n="359" facs="tcp:40747:9"/>ſome degree of wit and underſtanding; ſo I think it is very reaſonable that they ſhould be qualified with ſo much honeſty, as to be well affected to the Government as it is by Law eſtabliſhed. And to ſpeak properly it is not the Law that makes the Papiſts uncapable of Offices and Employments, it only declares they ſhall not be admitted, becauſe they were incapable before, and had made themſelves unfit to be truſted, partly through their dependance upon a forraign power, that is at enmity with the State, and ſeeks to ſubvert it, and partly by reaſon of that principle which they are poſſeſſed with, of its being their duty to deſtroy us whenſoever they can. And as it's a great favour vouchſafed by the Government, to ſuffer ſuch to live under it, as ſtand ſo ill affected to it, and want only means to overthrow it; ſo if the Roman Catholicks will not be content with the firſt without the latter, it will be a great temptation upon the Kingdom to deprive them of the Priviledge they have, becauſe they would not be content with it, unleſs they might obtain that which the Nation could not grant, without being <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> and without abandoning the means both of our ſafety here, and Happineſs hereafter. And whereas our Author takes the confidence to tell us, <hi>That there are many States and Cities in</hi> Germany, <hi>where without the giving occaſion to any diſturbance, the Government is ſhared between Papiſts and Proteſtants, and where both thoſe of the Roman Catholick and Reformed Religion, do equally partake in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Truſts and Employments:</hi> He muſt pardon me if I not only ſay, he is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, but that it is a down-right Falſehood, and that herein he betrays his wonted igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or at leaſt gives us a new diſcovery of the inſincerity that is natural to him. Nor would he have vented this in ſo general Terms, but that he did foreſee if he ſhould have condeſcended to particulars, how eaſy it would have been for perſons of very ordinary acquaintance either with Hiſtory or the World, to have both contradicted and refuted him. And if there were ſome one or other ſmall City, where by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Fewneſs of thoſe of one Religion to exerciſe the Government, and to take care of the Welfare of the Society, thoſe of the other Religion are ſometimes received into Employments, in order to prevent the inconveniencies which the want of a competent number of Magiſtrates would be attended with, and where the Jealouſie and Fear of being ſwallowed up by ſome envious and potent Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, may lay them under a neceſſity of agreeing better together than otherwiſe they would or than the principles of ſome of them incline them unto; muſt we thence conclude that it ought to be ſo in a great Kingdom, where there is ſo vaſt a number of Proteſtants admirably qualified with Wiſdom, Intereſt, and Eſtates, to diſcharge all the Offices of the Government, and to manage the univerſal care of the Society, without running the hazard of the many miſchiefs, that would accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the taking the Papiſts into partnerſhip with them? Nor could <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> in repreſenting what is ſafe or unſafe to ſo great and noble a Nation, take notice of what is practiſed upon neceſſity in ſome mean Town or Corporation, (ſuppoſing that it were there as our Author alledgeth) without tranſgreſſing againſt all the Rules both of prudence and decency. But as the <hi>Penſionary</hi> had no where in his <hi>Letter</hi> affirmed, that there were not any States or Cities, in which the Proteſtants and Papiſts bear Office in Government together; but had only ſaid, that Reaſon and Experience do ſhew us, how impoſſible it will be for them when joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in places of Truſt and publick Employments, to maintain a good Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence, and to live peaceably with one another; ſo this is found to be ſo juſt a truth, and ſo pertinently obſerved, that in all the places where it hath been practiſed (tho not in <hi>Germany,</hi> as our Author ignorantly ſuggeſts) they have not only lived in continual heats and diſſentions, but have often come to open Hoſtility againſt each other. Nor hath it meerly fallen out thus in private, and particular States with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, but the like evils have often followed and enſued where more States have aſſociated into Union for the common preſervation of the Generality; and where the Government hath been in ſome in the hands of Proteſtants, and in others executed by Roman Catholicks. Of this we have diverſe Examples in the <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where thro the Magiſtrates being in ſome <hi>Cantons</hi> of the Reformed, and in others of the Roman Catholick Religion, they have not only been often hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from joyning and acting vigorouſly, as they ought to have done, for the intereſt of all, and the benefit of the common Confederation and Union; but they have ſometimes come to open ruptures, and have been embarqued in War againſt one another. And foraſmuch as our Author makes bold to ſay, <hi>That there was never any Chriſtian Kingdom, where the Religion that the Prince profeſſeth, and which had in former ages been Dominant, was ſo far laid aſide and baniſhed, that his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects profeſſing the ſame with himſelf, were ſhut out and precluded from Truſts and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> I will take the freedom to tell him, that it is ſo groſs and palpable a
<pb n="360" facs="tcp:40747:10"/>Falſehood, that none but a perſon of his ignorance and impudence, would have had the face to have aſſerted it. For there are Chriſtian Kingdoms that have done more than this amounts unto, and who to prevent the danger of having Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts preferred to Truſts and Employments, in caſe a Prince of their Religion ſhould come to the Throne, have been ſo wiſe as to declare Roman Catholicks incapable either of obtaining or keeping the Soveraignty. And it was in the vertue of ſuch a Law, and by reaſon of the dread of it, that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> upon the having taken up a reſolution to turn Papiſt, choſe to demit her Crown before ſhe declared her ſelf, as knowing that immediately after ſuch a Declaration ſhe would have been depoſed from the Throne, and poſſibly not have had ſo liberal an allowance aſſigned her afterwards, as by that conduct ſhe did obtain. Nor is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to any, except it be to ſuch as our Author is for natural and acquired accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, that there were not only Laws in <hi>Scotland</hi> for precluding a Popiſh Prince from coming to the Government, but that the ſame thing was imployed in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> as being Oaths of ſuch a frame and nature that it had been moſt incongruous to impoſe them upon Subjects to a King of the Roman Catholick Religion. And tho theſe two Nations did not improve the advantage which they had by means of their legal proviſions, to hinder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King from inheriting the Crowns of the reſpective Realms; yet thoſe Laws ſerve to inform us, how far ſome Chriſtian Kingdoms thought it lawful to go, and to what heighth to Act, not only againſt Popiſh Subjects, but againſt Catholick Princes themſelves. Yea the time was, that the very Papiſts were ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the having men of their Religion debarred from Truſts and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Proteſtant Kingdoms under a Popiſh Prince, that they made the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws by which they are ſhut out from Offices and Declared incapable of them, the great Argument againſt the neceſſity of having the Bill paſſed for excluding the Duke of <hi>York</hi> from the Crown, and improved them as the main Engine for allaying the fears of the Nation, under the apprehenſions they had of his being a Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and coming to the Throne. But by their different Language now from what it was then, all Engliſhmen underſtand how far they are to be believed in other caſes: and whether the many promiſes which they do make at this time, in order to a further deſign, and the putting a new Trick upon the Nation, ought to be depended on by them whom they have already deceived. And whereas upon <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel's</hi> having obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the conduct of Roman Catholicks is much more ſevere towards Proteſtants, than that of thoſe of the Reformed Religion towards Papiſts, our Author is pleaſed to reply, <hi>that in order to judge as we ſhould of that different procedure, we are to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not leſs juſt, to baniſh a Religion that had been ſo long dominant as the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick had been; than to withſtand the introduction of a new Religion that would depreſs and ſupplant the old.</hi> All I ſhall ſay in reference to this, is that as it does not weaken, but in effect acknowledge what the <hi>Penſionary</hi> had ſaid; ſo by juſtifying what the Papiſts did, to prevent the bringing in of the Proteſtant Religion, which he ſtiles new; he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns us what we are to expect they will be ready to do, for the reintroducing the Papal Religion, to which he gives the character of old. Nor is it at all pertinent to the preſent caſe, which of the Religions is the oldeſt, or which is the neweſt; but all contended for is that the method's of the one, have been, and ſtill are, more ſevere and ſanguinary, than the methods of thoſe of the other. And as we believe our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be as ancient, as Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles; ſo no preſcription of time for Popery's having been in poſſeſſion, can deprive that which has the Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to warrant it, from a right of re-entrance.</p>
            <p>There remains only one thing to be ſpoken unto, of all that I undertook to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and correct our Author for, and that is the ſignal ingratitude of the Papiſts, and particularly of this Gentleman, to their Highneſſes, for all that Liberty, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and eaſe which Their Highneſſes were willing to have had allowed unto them. And that we may the more fully have an Idea of their unthankfulneſs, we are to conſider both the extent of that Liberty which Their Highneſſes were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to have had beſtowed upon them, and the obligations they would have come under for the rendring it hereafter inviolable. And all this not only at a ſeaſon, when many of the Papiſts carry it ſo undutifully towards their Highneſſes, but at a time when they of the Reformed Religion are ſo unhumanely perſecuted by ſeveral Popiſh Princes in other parts of the world. It had not been an unreaſonable deſire that before the Papiſts had been ſo importunate to have all Penal Laws againſt them in Proteſtant Nations reſcinded and taken away; that they ſhould have declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and improved their intereſt, for the Abrogation of all ſuch Laws as are in force againſt thoſe of the Reformed Religion in Popiſh Countries. And if their Highneſſes
<pb n="361" facs="tcp:40747:10"/>had inſiſted upon ſuch a ſtipulation, before They would have given their conſent for the Repeal of the Penal Laws againſt Roman Catholicks in <hi>England,</hi> it had been no more than what was agreeable to the Rules of Wiſdom and Juſtice. But their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes not thinking it fit to ſuffer their own mercy to be reſtrained by reaſon of the want of Chriſtian bowels in others, took the firſt opportunity put into their hands, of teſtifying their readineſs to conſent to the Repeal of all thoſe Laws againſt Papiſts in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by which they are made liable to fines or other puniſhments. And that thoſe which they can not agree to the reſcinding of, are only ſuch by which the Reformed Religion is covered from the deſigns of the Roman Catholicks againſt it, and by which they are reſtrained from getting into a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to overturn it. One would think that this ſhould have been received as a moſt ſpecial favour, and have obliged them to very hearty acknowledgments. Eſpecially when the Prince and Princeſs were willing to confirm both this and a Liberty for the private Exerciſe of their Religion with their Guaranty. But in ſtead of any ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of gratitude, there is nothing to be heard of from many of them, or to be met with in our Anſwerer, but what proclaims their diſſatisfaction, anger, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. For beſides all the ill returns, we have already taken notice of in this wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unthankful man; he tells us, that all which Their Highneſſes declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ready to conſent unto amounts only <hi>to the aboliſhing ſome cruel Laws, by which Romiſh Eccleſiaſticks ſtood condemned to death, for no other reaſon ſave their being Prieſts; and in the vertue of which, other perſons were baniſhed and deprived of their Eſtates, meerly for being Roman Catholicks; all which was a higher degree of barbarity than was ever pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed among the moſt ſalvage Nations.</hi> Now not to trouble my ſelf about what kind of entertainment, Romiſh Prieſts and Lay Papiſts have met with among thoſe Nations, which our Author ſtiles Barbarous, tho it will be found infinitely more ſevere, than any thing that was ever inflicted upon them in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> by reaſon of their Religion, or upon the ſcore of any Eccleſiaſtical Character: I would only know of this modeſt and veracious Gentleman, what he thinks of the barbarous and innumerable Cruelties, that were perpetrated in all ages and places heretofore, and which are at this day committed upon peaceable and ſincere Chriſtians, for no other crime but that they could not, and to this day cannot believe as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, nor continue in Communion with ſo idolatrous and villanous a Society. Whatſoever meaſure of ſeverity hath been any where exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed towards Papiſts, it was but according to the Preſident themſelves had ſet, in their dealing with them whom they ſtile Hereticks, and in which the Copy comes vaſtly below the Original. But then that which wholly alters the caſe, is, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Papiſts perſecute and deſtroy Chriſtians, meerly upon the account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there were never any ſevere, much leſs Sanguinary Laws enacted againſt them, ſave by reaſon of their Crimes againſt the State, and for being Enemies and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the Government. Popery was never perſecuted in <hi>England</hi> as it is a falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Belief; but as it binds men to the owning of a forraign, uſurped, and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Jurisdiction. 'Tis neither for their believing Tranſubſtantiation, nor for their Worſhipping Images, that Papiſts are adjudged to penalties or death; but becauſe they adhere to a forreign Enemy, and are treacherous to their Countrey. Could they have been but good Subjects; their being bad Chriſtians would never have preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced them. And indeed while they continue to hold that the Pope can depoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Soveraigns, and abſolve Subjects from their Allegiance to them, and that it is lawful to cut the Throats of all whom they ſtile Hereticks, and that all Laws made for our ſecurity are null and void, as being enacted by an incompetent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Authority, it would ſeem according to the exact meaſures of wiſdom and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that all lenity and favour towards them, were not only a ſupererogating in Mercy, but an indiſcretion in Policy. But then to let ſuch into the Government, were plainly to betray the State, and wilfully to abandon both it and our ſelves to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and ruined. Nor is there ſo much danger in advancing Robbers and Newgate Fellons to Employments, as there would be in preferring Papiſts, eſpecially if Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiced and Bigotted, into Civil Offices in a Reformed Kingdom. And therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they will not thankfully accept and quietly acquieſce in what is offered, and that rather from an exurberancy of Generoſity and Mercy, than from Maxims of prudence, and obligations ariſing from duty; it is beſt to leave them, to ſteer their own courſe, and to purſue thoſe Methods, which will infallibly iſſue in their diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to ſay no worſe. All ways of Gentleneſs and Moderation towards them, do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encourage their making the bolder claims, and the proceeding further in their uſurpations. The giving them an inch, provokes them to take an ell, and they grow enraged becauſe we will not tamely ſuffer it. If they act as they do, while the Chain
<pb n="362" facs="tcp:40747:11"/>hangs ſtill about their necks? what are we to expect if it ſhould be wholly taken off, &amp; they left looſe to exert the malignity which their Religion inſpires them with? For not being contented to invade and uſurp all ſorts of Employments and places of Truſt in defiance of the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws; they have aſſumed that confidence, as to make thoſe very Laws which were intentionally enacted and deſigned to keep Papiſts out of Office and Power, the ground and occaſion of incapacitating and ſhutting out Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. And whereas none are by Law to be admitted into Employments without making the Declarations contained in the <hi>Teſts;</hi> none are now to be continued, ſave they who ſhall both refuſe to take them, and withal promiſe to give their votes for the Election of ſuch perſons into Parliament, as ſhall be willing to Abrogate and Repeal them. Which is not only ſuch a piece of Chicannery in it ſelf, but ſuch an Aſſault upon the Legiſlative Authority, that it is hard to ſpeak of it, without more than uſual emotion of mind, and the having ones indignation ſtrangely excited and enflamed. However all I ſhall allow my ſelf at preſent to ſay, ſhall be only to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe all ſort of perſons to take care what they do, there being no Diſpenſing power lodged in the King, in reference to <hi>Penal,</hi> and much leſs in relation to the <hi>Teſt</hi> Laws. Of this we have a clear and uncontrollable proof in the proceedings of the Parliament 1673. when the Houſe of Commons voted the Declaration of the late King for Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience, to be both a violation of the Laws of the Land, and an altering of the Legiſlative power. Which is the more remarkable, in that it was not only done by the moſt obſequious Parliament that ever any King of <hi>England</hi> had, and of which many of the Members were his hired and brib'd <hi>Penſioners,</hi> but that they did thus adjudge, both after the King had acquainted them by a ſolemn Speech at the opening of the Seſſion, that he was Reſolved to adhere to his Declaration, and had endeavoured to <hi>Hector</hi> them into a departure from their Vote, by telling them in an Anſwer which he made to one of their Addreſſes, that they had queſtioned a power in the Crown, which had never been diſputed in the Reign of any of his Predeceſſors, and which belonged unto him as a prerogative inſeparable from the Soveraignty. Yet notwithſtanding both all this, and his applying himſelf in a Speech to the Houſe of Lords to have engaged them to ſtand by him againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, he was neceſſitated upon the Commons inſiſting, that there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any ſuch Diſpenſing power veſted in the Crown, nor claimed or exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any of his Predeceſſors; and that the aſſuming it was a changing of the Conſtitution, and an altering of the Legiſlative Authority; and upon the Lords declining to ſtand by him, and their adviſing him to give liberty by way of Bill to be paſſed into a Law; I ſay he was neceſſitated to take his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration off from the File, tear the Seal from it, and to aſſure both Houſes in a Speech he made to them, <hi>March</hi> 8. that what he had done in taking upon him to Suſpend the Penal Laws, ſhould not for the future be drawn either into conſequence or Example. In brief, if the Papiſts will not ſo far conſult their own intereſt, and comply with our ſafety, as to be contented with an eaſe from Penalties, and an Indulgence to be ratified into a Law for the private exerciſe of their Religion; it is the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable duty of all Proteſtants, of what party or perſwaſion ſoever they be, to unite together in withſtanding their endeavours and attempts for obtaining more. We have a laudable example in the carriage of all that pretended to Chriſtianity, when they were brought into a condition ſomewhat parallel with ours in one of the firſt Centuries. For tho the Orthodox had been perſecuted by the <hi>Arrians</hi> under <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Arrians</hi> harſhly enough treated at leaſt, as they thought for a while under <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> yet upon <hi>Julian</hi>'s coming to the Throne, both parties were ſo far from embracing his offers in order to revenge their wrongs upon one another, that they reſolved at that ſeaſon if not wholly to ſilence their Diſputes, yet to forbear all thoſe harſh Terms, that had enflamed their heats and animoſities. To which I ſhall add but this one thing more, and would beg of the Diſſenters, that they may ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider it, namely that as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were the only party of Chriſtians that made Addreſſes to <hi>Julian,</hi> and received favours from him; ſo they thereby became infamous, and were often afterwards reproached with it.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, I have ſtudyed to do what you required of me, and if it be my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune not to have acquitted my ſelf anſwerably to your expectations; yet the doing it as well, as the being bound up to an Author, that adminiſters ſo little occaſion for valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thoughts, would allow, gives me the ſatisfaction of having approved my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40747:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
